<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- name="GENERATOR" content="github.com/mmarkdown/mmark Mmark Markdown Processor - mmark.miek.nl" -->
<rfc version="3" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-mcconnell-software-status-wellknown-00" submissionType="independent" category="info" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" indexInclude="true">

<front>
<title abbrev="software-status-wellknown">A Well-Known URI for Software Lifecycle Status</title><seriesInfo value="draft-mcconnell-software-status-wellknown-00" stream="independent" status="informational" name="Internet-Draft"></seriesInfo>
<author initials="J." surname="McConnell" fullname="Jim McConnell"><organization>Ask McConnell, LLC</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>jim@askmcconnell.com</email>
<uri>https://askmcconnell.com</uri>
</address></author><date year="2026" month="April" day="14"></date>
<area>Applications</area>
<workgroup>Individual Submission</workgroup>
<keyword>software</keyword>
<keyword>lifecycle</keyword>
<keyword>end-of-life</keyword>
<keyword>EOL</keyword>
<keyword>supply chain</keyword>
<keyword>security</keyword>
<keyword>well-known</keyword>

<abstract>
<t>This document defines a Well-Known URI <xref target="RFC8615"></xref> at which software
vendors and open-source maintainers may publish machine-readable lifecycle
status information for their products. A JSON resource retrieved from
<tt>/.well-known/software-status.json</tt> allows consumers — including security
tools, software composition analysis (SCA) platforms, vulnerability scanners,
and system administrators — to programmatically determine whether a specific
version of a software product is actively supported, in long-term support
(LTS), under security-only maintenance, or at end-of-life (EOL).</t>
<t>This document also describes, in <eref target="#appendix-a">Appendix A</eref>, a companion convention for
open-source projects hosted on version-control platforms to publish equivalent
information within the repository at <tt>.github/software-status.json</tt>.</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction"><name>Introduction</name>
<t>Software products have defined lifecycles. Vendors release versions, provide
security patches and bug fixes for a period, and eventually discontinue
support. When support ends, no further patches are issued — including patches
for newly discovered security vulnerabilities. End-of-life (EOL) software
represents a significant and persistent risk in organizational environments,
as it may remain deployed indefinitely after its support window closes.</t>
<t>Determining whether a specific version of software is currently supported
requires manual research: locating the vendor's lifecycle policy page,
interpreting its contents, and correlating the installed version against
published support dates. This process is not standardized, not machine-
readable, and not reliable at scale. Many vendors do not publish structured
lifecycle data at all. Security tools that attempt to automate EOL detection
must resort to web scraping, curated third-party databases, or inference —
all of which introduce latency, inaccuracy, and maintenance burden.</t>
<t>This document proposes a simple, low-overhead mechanism for software vendors
and maintainers to publish authoritative lifecycle data in a machine-readable
format at a predictable location, using the Well-Known URI mechanism defined
in <xref target="RFC8615"></xref>.</t>
<t>The design goals are:</t>

<ul>
<li><t><strong>Authoritative</strong>: lifecycle data is published directly by the party that
controls the software's support policy — the vendor or maintainer.</t>
</li>
<li><t><strong>Machine-readable</strong>: a single, well-defined JSON format that any
consuming tool can parse without scraping or inference.</t>
</li>
<li><t><strong>Low barrier</strong>: adding a static JSON file to an existing web presence
requires minimal effort and no new infrastructure.</t>
</li>
<li><t><strong>Incrementally deployable</strong>: absence of the resource (HTTP 404) is a
well-defined signal. Tools can fall back to existing methods when the
resource is not present.</t>
</li>
<li><t><strong>Composable</strong>: the same schema is used for both the Well-Known URI
(<eref target="#appendix-a">Appendix A</eref> describes the version-control companion) so tools that
understand one format understand both.</t>
</li>
</ul>

<section anchor="conventions-and-definitions"><name>Conventions and Definitions</name>
<t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;, &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;,
&quot;SHOULD&quot;, &quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;NOT RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;MAY&quot;, and
&quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this document are to be interpreted as described in
BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"></xref> <xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and only when, they appear in all
capitals, as shown here.</t>
<t>The following terms are used in this document:</t>
<t><strong>Software product</strong>: A discrete, identifiable unit of software that has
a defined vendor or maintainer and a versioned release history.</t>
<t><strong>Version series</strong>: A major or minor version designation under which
multiple patch releases may be issued (e.g., &quot;3.2&quot; covering 3.2.0, 3.2.1,
3.2.2, etc.).</t>
<t><strong>End-of-life (EOL)</strong>: A state in which a vendor or maintainer has
permanently ceased issuing any updates, including security patches, for a
given version series.</t>
<t><strong>Long-Term Support (LTS)</strong>: A designated version series for which the
vendor or maintainer commits to an extended support window, typically
longer than the standard release lifecycle.</t>
<t><strong>Consuming tool</strong>: Any software system that retrieves and processes a
<tt>software-status.json</tt> resource, including security scanners, SCA tools,
package managers, and monitoring systems.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="the-software-status-json-resource"><name>The software-status.json Resource</name>

<section anchor="location-and-retrieval"><name>Location and Retrieval</name>
<t>A software vendor or maintainer that wishes to publish lifecycle status
information for software associated with a domain SHOULD publish a
<tt>software-status.json</tt> resource at the Well-Known URI:</t>

<artwork><![CDATA[https://example.com/.well-known/software-status.json
]]></artwork>
<t>The resource MUST be served over HTTPS. HTTP retrieval MAY be supported
for compatibility but consuming tools SHOULD prefer HTTPS and SHOULD warn
or fail if only HTTP is available.</t>
<t>The resource MUST be served with a Content-Type of <tt>application/json</tt>.</t>
<t>If no lifecycle information is available or the vendor has not adopted this
convention, the server SHOULD return HTTP 404. Consuming tools MUST treat a
404 response as &quot;no declaration available&quot; and fall back to other methods.
Consuming tools MUST NOT treat a 404 as evidence that the software is
end-of-life.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="caching"><name>Caching</name>
<t>The resource SHOULD include standard HTTP caching headers. A <tt>max-age</tt> of
604800 (seven days) is RECOMMENDED for resources that are infrequently
updated. Consuming tools SHOULD respect <tt>Cache-Control</tt> and <tt>Expires</tt>
headers.</t>
<t>In the absence of explicit caching headers, consuming tools SHOULD cache
a successfully retrieved resource for no fewer than 24 hours and no more
than 30 days.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="the-software-status-json-schema"><name>The software-status.json Schema</name>
<t>The <tt>software-status.json</tt> resource is a JSON object (<xref target="RFC8259"></xref>) with
the following structure.</t>

<section anchor="root-object"><name>Root Object</name>
<t>The root object MUST contain the following fields:</t>

<dl spacing="compact">
<dt><tt>schema_version</tt> (string, REQUIRED):</dt>
<dd>The version of this schema. This document defines version <tt>&quot;1.0&quot;</tt>.
Consuming tools that encounter an unrecognized schema version SHOULD
process fields they recognize and ignore fields they do not.</dd>
<dt><tt>name</tt> (string, REQUIRED):</dt>
<dd>The human-readable name of the software product.</dd>
<dt><tt>vendor</tt> (string, REQUIRED):</dt>
<dd>The name of the organization or individual responsible for the software's
support lifecycle.</dd>
<dt><tt>versions</tt> (array, REQUIRED):</dt>
<dd>An array of version entry objects as described in <eref target="#version-entries">Section 4.2</eref>.
MUST contain at least one entry. SHOULD include all version series for
which the vendor has a defined support position, including EOL versions.</dd>
</dl>
<t>The root object MAY contain the following fields:</t>

<dl spacing="compact">
<dt><tt>homepage</tt> (string):</dt>
<dd>A URI for the software product's primary website.</dd>
<dt><tt>source</tt> (string):</dt>
<dd>A URI for the software's canonical source repository.</dd>
<dt><tt>package_identifiers</tt> (object):</dt>
<dd>A map of package ecosystem names to the identifier used in that ecosystem.
See <eref target="#package-identifiers">Section 4.4</eref>.</dd>
<dt><tt>release_cycle_url</tt> (string):</dt>
<dd>A URI for the vendor's official support lifecycle or release policy page.</dd>
<dt><tt>last_updated</tt> (string):</dt>
<dd>An ISO 8601 date string indicating when this resource was last reviewed
or updated (e.g., <tt>&quot;2026-04-14&quot;</tt>). Consuming tools MAY use this field to
decide whether to re-fetch the resource regardless of caching policy.</dd>
</dl>
</section>

<section anchor="version-entries"><name>Version Entries</name>
<t>Each object in the <tt>versions</tt> array represents one version series and MUST
contain the following fields:</t>

<dl spacing="compact">
<dt><tt>version</tt> (string, REQUIRED):</dt>
<dd>The version series identifier. This MAY be a specific version number
(<tt>&quot;3.2&quot;</tt>), a major version with wildcard (<tt>&quot;2.x&quot;</tt>), a named track
(<tt>&quot;LTS 22.04&quot;</tt>), or any string that meaningfully identifies the series
to the vendor's users.</dd>
<dt><tt>status</tt> (string, REQUIRED):</dt>
<dd>The current support status of this version series. MUST be one of the
values defined in <eref target="#status-values">Section 4.3</eref>.</dd>
</dl>
<t>Each version entry MAY contain the following fields:</t>

<dl spacing="compact">
<dt><tt>release_date</tt> (string):</dt>
<dd>An ISO 8601 date on which this version series reached general availability.</dd>
<dt><tt>support_ends</tt> (string or null):</dt>
<dd>An ISO 8601 date on which support for this version series is scheduled
to end. A value of <tt>null</tt> indicates no currently planned end date.
SHOULD be present for all version series where a planned end date is
known.</dd>
<dt><tt>eol_date</tt> (string):</dt>
<dd>An ISO 8601 date on which this version series reached end-of-life. This
field records a past event; <tt>support_ends</tt> records a future one.
SHOULD be present when <tt>status</tt> is <tt>&quot;eol&quot;</tt> and the date is known.</dd>
<dt><tt>lts</tt> (boolean):</dt>
<dd><tt>true</tt> if this version series is designated as Long-Term Support.
Defaults to <tt>false</tt> if absent.</dd>
<dt><tt>notes</tt> (string):</dt>
<dd>A human-readable note providing additional context about this version
entry. Consuming tools MAY surface this to users but MUST NOT rely on
its content for programmatic decisions.</dd>
</dl>
</section>

<section anchor="status-values"><name>Status Values</name>
<t>The <tt>status</tt> field MUST be one of the following values:</t>

<dl spacing="compact">
<dt><tt>&quot;active&quot;</tt>:</dt>
<dd>The version series is fully supported. The vendor intends to issue
bug fixes, security patches, and potentially new features.</dd>
<dt><tt>&quot;lts&quot;</tt>:</dt>
<dd>The version series is designated Long-Term Support. The vendor commits
to issuing security patches (and possibly bug fixes) for an extended
period.</dd>
<dt><tt>&quot;security-only&quot;</tt>:</dt>
<dd>The version series is no longer receiving general bug fixes or new
features, but security vulnerabilities are still being patched.</dd>
<dt><tt>&quot;eol&quot;</tt>:</dt>
<dd>The version series has reached end-of-life. No further patches of any
kind will be issued, including security patches.</dd>
<dt><tt>&quot;unmaintained&quot;</tt>:</dt>
<dd>The software project has been abandoned by its original maintainer.
No patches are expected, but the project has not been formally
declared end-of-life.</dd>
</dl>
<t>Additional status values MAY be defined in future revisions of this
document. Consuming tools that encounter an unrecognized status value
SHOULD treat it as equivalent to <tt>&quot;unknown&quot;</tt> and note the unrecognized
value in any user-facing output.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="package-identifiers"><name>Package Identifiers</name>
<t>The optional <tt>package_identifiers</tt> object maps package ecosystem names
to the string identifier used in that ecosystem. Known ecosystem names
include, but are not limited to:</t>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Key</th>
<th align="left">Ecosystem</th>
<th align="left">Example value</th>
</tr>
</thead>

<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left"><tt>pypi</tt></td>
<td align="left">Python Package Index</td>
<td align="left"><tt>&quot;requests&quot;</tt></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left"><tt>npm</tt></td>
<td align="left">npm registry</td>
<td align="left"><tt>&quot;express&quot;</tt></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left"><tt>rubygems</tt></td>
<td align="left">RubyGems</td>
<td align="left"><tt>&quot;rails&quot;</tt></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left"><tt>cargo</tt></td>
<td align="left">crates.io</td>
<td align="left"><tt>&quot;tokio&quot;</tt></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left"><tt>nuget</tt></td>
<td align="left">NuGet</td>
<td align="left"><tt>&quot;Newtonsoft.Json&quot;</tt></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left"><tt>maven</tt></td>
<td align="left">Maven Central</td>
<td align="left"><tt>&quot;org.apache:commons&quot;</tt></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left"><tt>apt</tt></td>
<td align="left">Debian/Ubuntu APT</td>
<td align="left"><tt>&quot;openssl&quot;</tt></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left"><tt>brew</tt></td>
<td align="left">Homebrew</td>
<td align="left"><tt>&quot;openssl&quot;</tt></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left"><tt>docker</tt></td>
<td align="left">Docker Hub</td>
<td align="left"><tt>&quot;library/nginx&quot;</tt></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left"><tt>github</tt></td>
<td align="left">GitHub repository</td>
<td align="left"><tt>&quot;owner/repo&quot;</tt></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table><t>A value of <tt>null</tt> for a given key indicates the software is not
distributed through that ecosystem.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="processing-rules-for-consuming-tools"><name>Processing Rules for Consuming Tools</name>

<section anchor="discovery"><name>Discovery</name>
<t>To retrieve lifecycle status for software associated with a known domain,
a consuming tool SHOULD:</t>

<ol spacing="compact">
<li>Construct the URI <tt>https://{domain}/.well-known/software-status.json</tt></li>
<li>Issue an HTTP GET request with an <tt>Accept: application/json</tt> header</li>
<li>Treat a 2xx response containing valid JSON as a successful retrieval</li>
<li>Treat a 404 or 410 response as &quot;no declaration&quot; and fall back</li>
<li>Treat other error responses (5xx, timeouts) as transient failures;
retry with exponential backoff before treating as unavailable</li>
</ol>
</section>

<section anchor="version-matching"><name>Version Matching</name>
<t>When matching an installed version against the <tt>versions</tt> array, consuming
tools SHOULD use the following logic:</t>

<ol spacing="compact">
<li>Attempt an exact match on the <tt>version</tt> field</li>
<li>If no exact match, attempt a prefix match: an installed version of
<tt>3.2.7</tt> matches a version series of <tt>3.2</tt></li>
<li>If no prefix match, attempt a major-version match: <tt>3.2.7</tt> matches
<tt>3.x</tt></li>
<li>If no match is found, treat the version's lifecycle status as unknown</li>
</ol>
<t>When multiple entries match, consuming tools SHOULD prefer the most
specific match (exact &gt; prefix &gt; major-version).</t>
</section>

<section anchor="conflict-resolution"><name>Conflict Resolution</name>
<t>When a consuming tool has lifecycle data for a product from multiple
sources (e.g., a third-party database and a <tt>software-status.json</tt>
resource), data retrieved from <tt>software-status.json</tt> SHOULD be treated
as authoritative and given precedence, as it represents a declaration
by the party responsible for the software's support policy.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations"><name>Security Considerations</name>

<section anchor="authenticity"><name>Authenticity</name>
<t>The <tt>software-status.json</tt> resource is served over HTTPS and inherits
the authenticity guarantees of the TLS connection. A consuming tool
that retrieves the resource over HTTPS from the vendor's canonical domain
can be reasonably confident that the content reflects the vendor's intent.</t>
<t>Consuming tools MUST NOT retrieve this resource over plain HTTP and treat
it as authoritative. Consuming tools SHOULD validate that the hostname of
the retrieval URI matches the domain associated with the software in
question.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="denial-of-service"><name>Denial of Service</name>
<t>A consuming tool that retrieves <tt>software-status.json</tt> resources at scale
SHOULD implement rate limiting, caching, and exponential backoff to avoid
placing undue load on vendor infrastructure.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="misleading-declarations"><name>Misleading Declarations</name>
<t>This mechanism relies on vendors publishing accurate information. A vendor
could theoretically publish a <tt>software-status.json</tt> that misrepresents
the support status of a product — for example, declaring an EOL product
as <tt>&quot;active&quot;</tt> to discourage users from migrating. Consuming tools SHOULD
note the source of lifecycle determinations in user-facing output so that
users can evaluate the claim in context.</t>
<t>Consuming tools that maintain independent lifecycle databases MAY flag
discrepancies between their own records and a vendor-published
<tt>software-status.json</tt> for human review.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="privacy"><name>Privacy</name>
<t>Retrieving <tt>software-status.json</tt> from a vendor's domain may reveal to
that vendor that a consuming tool is checking lifecycle status, potentially
disclosing information about what software is deployed in an organization.
Consuming tools operating in sensitive environments SHOULD consider
whether direct retrieval is appropriate or whether a privacy-preserving
intermediary (such as a shared cache or mirroring service) should be used.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations"><name>IANA Considerations</name>

<section anchor="well-known-uri-registration"><name>Well-Known URI Registration</name>
<t>IANA is requested to register the following Well-Known URI in the
&quot;Well-Known URIs&quot; registry established by <xref target="RFC8615"></xref>:</t>

<dl spacing="compact">
<dt>URI suffix:</dt>
<dd><tt>software-status.json</tt></dd>
<dt>Change controller:</dt>
<dd>IETF</dd>
<dt>Specification document(s):</dt>
<dd>This document</dd>
<dt>Related information:</dt>
<dd>This URI returns a JSON document describing the software lifecycle
status for products associated with the host. The format is defined
in <eref target="#the-software-statusjson-schema">Section 4</eref> of this document.</dd>
</dl>
</section>
</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references><name>References</name>
<references><name>Normative References</name>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8259.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8615.xml"/>
</references>
<references><name>Informative References</name>
<xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9116.xml"/>
</references>
</references>

<section anchor="examples"><name>Examples</name>

<section anchor="minimal-resource"><name>Minimal Resource</name>

<sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[{
  "schema_version": "1.0",
  "name": "ExampleDB",
  "vendor": "Example Software Inc.",
  "versions": [
    {
      "version": "5.0",
      "status": "active",
      "support_ends": null
    }
  ]
}
]]></sourcecode>
</section>

<section anchor="multi-version-resource-with-eol-history"><name>Multi-Version Resource with EOL History</name>

<sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[{
  "schema_version": "1.0",
  "name": "ExampleDB",
  "vendor": "Example Software Inc.",
  "homepage": "https://example.com/db",
  "package_identifiers": {
    "apt": "exampledb-server",
    "docker": "exampleinc/exampledb"
  },
  "versions": [
    {
      "version": "5.0",
      "release_date": "2025-03-01",
      "status": "active",
      "support_ends": null,
      "lts": false
    },
    {
      "version": "4.2",
      "release_date": "2023-06-15",
      "status": "lts",
      "support_ends": "2027-06-15",
      "lts": true,
      "notes": "LTS release — security and critical bug fixes through June 2027"
    },
    {
      "version": "4.0",
      "release_date": "2022-01-10",
      "status": "security-only",
      "support_ends": "2026-01-10",
      "lts": false
    },
    {
      "version": "3.x",
      "release_date": "2019-04-01",
      "status": "eol",
      "eol_date": "2024-04-01",
      "support_ends": "2024-04-01",
      "lts": false
    }
  ],
  "release_cycle_url": "https://example.com/support-policy",
  "last_updated": "2026-04-14"
}
]]></sourcecode>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="appendix-a"><name>Companion Convention: Repository-Hosted Lifecycle Status</name>
<t>This appendix describes a companion convention for software projects
hosted on version-control platforms (such as GitHub, GitLab, or Gitea).
This convention is informative and does not define a standards-track
mechanism; it is documented here because it uses the same schema as the
Well-Known URI defined in this document and is intended to be consumed
by the same tools.</t>

<section anchor="motivation"><name>Motivation</name>
<t>Many software projects are distributed as source code and do not have a
corresponding web domain from which a Well-Known URI could be served.
Open-source libraries, developer tools, and components published to
package registries often have a repository URL as their primary identity,
not a product domain.</t>
<t>For these projects, a file committed to a predictable location within the
repository serves the same purpose as the Well-Known URI.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="location"><name>Location</name>
<t>The resource SHOULD be placed at:</t>

<artwork><![CDATA[{repository-root}/.github/software-status.json
]]></artwork>
<t>The <tt>.github/</tt> directory is an established convention on major version-
control platforms for repository-level metadata. This location is
intentionally analogous to <tt>.github/SECURITY.md</tt>, <tt>.github/FUNDING.yml</tt>,
and similar files.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="discovery-1"><name>Discovery</name>
<t>Consuming tools that resolve a software package to a GitHub-hosted
repository SHOULD check for the presence of this file at the raw content
URL:</t>

<artwork><![CDATA[https://raw.githubusercontent.com/{owner}/{repo}/HEAD/.github/software-status.json
]]></artwork>
<t>A 404 response MUST be treated as &quot;no declaration available&quot;. A 200
response with valid JSON MUST be processed according to the schema
defined in <eref target="#the-software-statusjson-schema">Section 4</eref>.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="schema"><name>Schema</name>
<t>The <tt>.github/software-status.json</tt> resource uses the same JSON schema
as defined in <eref target="#the-software-statusjson-schema">Section 4</eref>, with one addition:
the <tt>source</tt> field at the root object SHOULD be set to the canonical
repository URI.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="precedence"><name>Precedence</name>
<t>When a project has both a Well-Known URI resource and a repository-hosted
resource, consuming tools SHOULD prefer the Well-Known URI, as it is
served from infrastructure explicitly controlled by the vendor and subject
to the HTTPS authenticity guarantees described in <eref target="#security-considerations">Section 6</eref>.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="example"><name>Example</name>

<sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[{
  "schema_version": "1.0",
  "name": "example-lib",
  "vendor": "Example Org",
  "source": "https://github.com/example/example-lib",
  "package_identifiers": {
    "pypi": "example-lib",
    "npm": null
  },
  "versions": [
    {
      "version": "2.0",
      "release_date": "2025-01-01",
      "status": "active",
      "support_ends": null
    },
    {
      "version": "1.x",
      "release_date": "2022-06-01",
      "status": "eol",
      "eol_date": "2025-06-01"
    }
  ],
  "last_updated": "2026-04-14"
}
]]></sourcecode>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="related-work"><name>Related Work</name>
<t><strong>endoflife.date</strong>: A community-maintained database of software lifecycle
information, available at <tt>https://endoflife.date</tt>. Provides an API for
querying EOL dates for approximately 400 products. This proposal is
complementary: endoflife.date is a centralized catalog; <tt>software-status.json</tt>
is a decentralized, vendor-authoritative mechanism. Consuming tools should
use both.</t>
<t><strong>security.txt</strong> (<xref target="RFC9116"></xref>): Defines a Well-Known URI (<tt>/.well-known/
security.txt</tt>) at which organizations publish security contact information.
This proposal follows the same pattern for lifecycle data.</t>
<t><strong>Software Bill of Materials (SBOM)</strong>: Formats including CycloneDX and SPDX
describe the components present in a software artifact. SBOMs identify
<em>what</em> is present; <tt>software-status.json</tt> declares the lifecycle status of
<em>what</em> is present. The two are complementary: an SBOM tool that resolves
component origins can use <tt>software-status.json</tt> to annotate each component
with its current support status.</t>
<t><strong>NIST Secure Software Development Framework (SSDF)</strong>: The SSDF (NIST SP
800-218) recommends that organizations track the EOL status of software
components they depend on. This proposal provides a standardized data source
for that activity.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="acknowledgements"><name>Acknowledgements</name>
<t>The author thanks the maintainers of endoflife.date for their sustained
effort in curating software lifecycle data, which demonstrated both the
value of this information and the limitations of a purely centralized
approach. The design of this proposal was informed by operational experience
building S3C-Tool (<eref target="https://askmcconnell.com/s3c/">https://askmcconnell.com/s3c/</eref>), a software supply chain
security tool that performs EOL assessment at scale.</t>
</section>

</back>

</rfc>
